בוקר טוב, Boker tov, ערב פסח, erev Pesach, don't forget to do
your ביעור חמץ biur chametz and your ביטול. bittul. Today's דף daf
is מ"ב mem bet and extremely
appropriately, can you get that? The oh it's open, oh hi. And
extremely appropriately the דף daf is for is dealing with the issue
of שליחות shlichut and one of the main sources of שליחות shlichut
is the idea of שחיטה shechting the קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, which
was done today. So, we have three sources of שליחות, shlichut, one
is
תרומה, terumah, גם אתם, gam atem, even you, which includes a שליח,
shaliach, one is גירושין, gerushin, ושלח ושילחה מביתו, veshilach veshilchah mibeito, literally
send or drive her out of the house, but understood to mean
he can make a שליח, shaliach, and one is קרבן פסח korban
Pesach because it says ושחטו אתו כל קהל עדת ישראל, veshachatu oto
kol kehal adat Yisrael, which means is interpreted to mean every individual's
obligated, and even though every individual's obligated we know that every individual
did not שחיטה shecht it, one person שחיטה shechted for each family.
The גמרא Gemara quoted a ברייתא baraisa about losing a קרבן פסח,
korban Pesach, but that really wasn't even משנה mishna necessarily because I
mean excuse me a משנה, mishna, but that wasn't even necessary, it's
really just understood from the case itself that one not that one
person שחיטה shechts for the group, even though from the פסוק pasuk
ושחטו כל עדת ישראל veshachatu kol adat Yisrael it sounds like each
person is obligated. So all of those show you an idea of
שליחות shlichut and the גמרא Gemara said you really could have learned
it out from two of them, from קדשים kodshim from the קרבן
פסח korban Pesach and from קידושין kiddushin and גירושין gerushin
because you can't just learn קידושין kiddushin and גירושין, gerushin, you wouldn't
have known things that are קדוש. kodesh. So
but you couldn't have just learned from the קרבן פסח korban Pesach
because that's done במחשבה, b'machshavah, you can sanctify things just by thought.
So therefore but by taking those two extremes you include everything in
the middle. All right, so the גמרא Gemara wants to know why
you need the פסוק pasuk by תרומה terumah and that's where we
pick up on מ"א עמוד ב'. mem alef amud bet. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: ואלא אתם גם אתם למה
לי. Ve'ella atem gam atem lama li. Right, so
the word אתם, atem, line starts with the word אתם, atem, about
I don't know twenty about two-thirds of the way down. ואלא אתם
גם אתם למה לי. Ve'ella atem gam atem lama li. So why
do you need then the פסוק pasuk אתם atem even you, you
even you by תרומה terumah which seems to include a שליח shaliach
if we can learn שליח shaliach from these other two sources? So
the גמרא Gemara says מדתניא midtanya כדרבי ינאי, k'de'Rabbi Yannai, you need
it like the teaching of Rabbi Yannai, דאמר רבי ינאי, damar Rabbi
Yannai, גם אתם gam atem even you, what does that teach? Not
to include a שליח, shaliach, we start with knowing a שליח shaliach
works and it's to define the parameters of a שליח, shaliach, גם
אתם gam atem even your שליח shaliach has to be like you.
What does that mean like you? מה אתם בני ברית אף שלוחיכם
בני ברית. Ma atem bnei berit af shluchaichon bnei berit. The same
way your שליח shaliach is part of the covenant, is a Jew,
you are a Jew, your שליח shaliach has to be part of
the covenant. So therefore you cannot make a non-Jew as your שליח.
shaliach. Okay, so the it's coming to teach not the idea of
שליחות shlichut but parameters of שליחות, shlichut, has to be in similar
to you. So גמרא Gemara says הא למה לי קרא? ha lama
li kra? Why do I need a פסוק? pasuk? I could learn
it מסברא misvara מדרבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן נפקא. mid'Rabbi
Chiya bar Abba ammar Rabbi Yochanan nafka. I could learn it from
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba in the name of Rabbi Yochanan. דאמר רבי
חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן Damar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba ammar
Rabbi Yochanan אין העבד נעשה שליח לקבל גט מיד בעלה של אשה
לפי שאינו בתורת גיטין וקידושין. ein ha'eved na'aseh shaliach lekabel get miyad
ba'alah shel isha lefi she'eino betorat gittin vekiddushin. A woman, a slave
cannot be a שליח shaliach to accept a גט get on behalf
of a woman from her husband because marriage does not apply to
him. Slaves the הלכה halakha does not recognize marriage and divorce by
slaves and therefore says the גמרא Gemara here
that what do you call it, says the גמרא Gemara that
we know that he could not be a שליח shaliach because he's
not בתורת, betorat, בתורת גיטין וקידושין. betorat gittin vekiddushin. If the laws
don't apply to you of a certain category you cannot serve as
an agent for a whole category of laws that are irrelevant to
you. Okay, so therefore even though an עבד eved is considered בני
ברית, bnei berit, an עבד eved is in the covenant, an עבד
eved is partially obligated in מצוות. mitzvot. So I can make an
עבד eved to be my שליח shaliach to take תרומות ומעשרות terumot
umaasrot because an עבד eved isn't allowed to eat טבל tevel and
I could make an עבד eved my שליח shaliach to purchase something
for me or sell something for me but he can't be a
שליח shaliach in an area of law that doesn't apply to him
in the area of גיטין gittin and קידושין. kiddushin. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says if I know that just מסברא misvara that you
have to be in the same category of law why do I
need a פסוק pasuk to exclude a non-Jew from תרומה? terumah? Wouldn't
a non-Jew obviously be excluded from תרומה terumah because a non-Jew doesn't
take תרומה? terumah? So obviously he can't be a שליח. shaliach. Why
would I need a פסוק? pasuk? So the גמרא Gemara says, גמרא
Gemara says where is it? איצטריכא, Itzricha, I need the פסוק. pasuk.
סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka deitach amina, I would have thought, עבד דלאו
בר התרה הוא כלל, eved delav bar hatara hu klal,
an עבד eved is not in the category of being permitted by
a גט. get. גיטין Gittin and קידושין kiddushin don't apply to an
עבד, eved, he's categorically excluded. So there I know that even though
he's in the category of
בני ברית, bnei berit, he's excluded because he's not בתורת. betorat. those
הלכות halakhot don't apply to him. Okay, but I might have thought
the opposite by a non-Jew when it comes to taking תרומה. terumah.
אבל עובד כוכבים, aval oved kochavim, a non-Jew, הווי איתא בתרומה? hovei
itah b'terumah? A non-Jew can take תרומה terumah for himself and in
his own grain. דתנן, detnan, we taught in the משנה, mishnah, העובד
כוכבים והכותי שתרמו תרומתן תרומה. ha-oved kochavim veha-kuti she-tarmu terumatan terumah. If
a non-Jew or Samaritan takes תרומה, terumah, it's valid. Okay, רש"י Rashi
says some of this has to do with the question of when
a non-Jew owns land in the land of Israel, does it change
the status of the land? This would have to assume it doesn't
change the status of the land. When a non-Jew with, you know,
sort of smooths out the grain and processes the grain, does that
make it exempt? All of this assumes that the non-Jew's ownership and
processing does not exempt the grain. And then the... so but if
you take those assumptions, then a non-Jew actually can separate תרומה. terumah.
It says if, like, the Jew grew it and the non-Jew bought
it, other types of scenarios, a non-Jew taking תרומה terumah actually is
valid. Okay, and the תרומה terumah has a status of תרומה. terumah.
So therefore I might think אימא שליח נמי עביד, eima shaliach nami
avid, maybe you can be a שליח shaliach for taking your תרומה.
terumah. קמשמע לן kamashma lan that he can't. Okay, so the point
is, you know, you could have said another thing. How about just
a שליח shaliach in a non-ritual matter? How about a שליח shaliach
to buy and sell stuff for me? Right? The תורה Torah הלכה
halakhah recognizes ownership, you know, and buying and selling of non-Jews. So
there's really two separate categories. And a שליח shaliach has to be
both. Number one is he has to be Jewish, even if the
area of law applies to him. So תרומה, terumah, buying and selling,
those types of things that applies to non-Jews. Nevertheless, he can't be
my שליח shaliach because he's not Jewish or he's not בני ברית.
b'nei brit. Okay, number two is even if he is בני ברית,
b'nei brit, obligated in מצוות, mitzvot, he can't be a שליח shaliach
if he's excluded categorically from this system of laws. And therefore an
עבד, eved, although he's obligated in מצוות, mitzvot, can't be a שליח
shaliach for גיטין gitin and קידושין. kidushin. Okay, but that's what you
learn out from גם אתם. gam atem. בני ברית b'nei brit you
know logically that the area of laws has to apply and from
גם אתם gam atem you learn out that a שליח shaliach has
to be Jewish. Yes.
Shliach— Tosefta uses נכרי nochri rather than גוי goy in the משנה.
mishnah. Yeah, really?
That's... I mean I don't know, I can't tell you about that.
He usually
changes עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim to גוי. goy. Yeah, I don't know,
maybe that's just the original משנה. mishnah. Anyway, okay. Now, the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
ורבי שמעון דפטר, u'Rebbi Shimon d'patar, but according to רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon that says that when a non-Jew takes תרומה terumah it does
not have the status of תרומה. terumah. דתנן, detnan, we taught in
the משנה, mishnah, תרומת עובד כוכבים מדמעת. terumat oved kochavim medama'at. A
תרומה terumah of a non-Jew that a non-Jew separated causes דמוע, dimua,
it gets mixed up with other grain. It makes the rest of
the grain, you know,
only edible by a כהן. kohen. It's seen as a mixture of
תרומה terumah and non-תרומה. terumah. וחייבין עליה חומש, ve'chayavin aleha chomesh, and
if you were to eat it or whatever, you would have to
pay it back with an extra fifth. So meaning the תרומה terumah
of a non-Jew has a real status of תרומה. terumah. Okay, that's
the תנא קמא. tanna kamma. That's what we've been saying. רבי שמעון
פוטר, Rebbi Shimon poter, רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon exempts. He says if
a non-Jew takes תרומה, terumah, it does not have a status of
תרומה. terumah. It only can be separated by a Jew. So according
to him, אתם גם אתם atem gam atem למה לי? lama li?
When would you ever need to have this הלכה halakhah that a
שליח shaliach can only be Jewish? Because there's never an area where
a non-Jew is in the category of law that you would need
to exclude him by virtue of him being a non-Jew. So the
גמרא Gemara says, again, I don't know why you can't just say
what do you call it, like an area of מקח וממכר, mekach
u'mimkar, you know, buying and selling things. But anyway the גמרא Gemara
says, no.
אצטריך, itzterich, I need this הלכה halakhah to exclude... I need the
גם אתם gam atem to tell me the following thing. סלקא דעתך
אמינא, salka da'tach amina, I would have thought to say, הא אמר
מר אתם ולא אריסים אתם ולא שותפין אתם ולא אפוטרופוס. ha amar
mar atem ve'lo arisim atem ve'lo shutafin atem ve'lo apitropus. So אתם,
atem, the word אתם, atem, before you get to the גם, gam,
the גם gam includes a שליח, shaliach, but the word אתם atem
is a more limiting word. So the word אתם atem limits that
there are certain people that cannot take תרומה terumah who aren't you
and aren't your agent. Who's not me and not my agent and
nevertheless, you know, it's like that wise men of Chelm joke, right?
Whatever, anyway. The story, this guy goes to your, you know, and
starts telling somebody tell a riddle. You know, חיים Chaim tells a
riddle. It says, okay, who is it that is like, you know,
that's my father's son but not my brother? So it says, it's
me. So he's brilliant. So he goes back and he says, okay,
I have a riddle. Who is it that's my father's son and
not my brother? So nobody in the town knows. So he says,
it's חיים יאנקל. Chaim Yankel. Okay. Anyway. Okay. Anyway,
so who is it? I'm sorry.
First time that got such a laugh. Okay. Anyway. Who... okay, who
is it? Who is it that's not me and not my שליח
shaliach that I might think might still be able to take תרומה
terumah that the פסוק pasuk has to exclude? So אתם atem is
saying it's only you and גם gam is your שליח. shaliach. But
still, but not somebody who's not you and not your שליח. shaliach.
Who is that person? So it says אתם ולא אריסים, atem ve'lo
arisim, not your sharecropper. Okay, maybe he can take on his portion,
he can't take on your portion. ולא שותפין, ve'lo shutafin, not a
partner. Again, can take on his portion, not yours. אתם ולא אפוטרופוס.
atem ve'lo apitropus. Not a, not somebody who's like who's an overseer,
you know, for like, for like what do you call it, for
like orphans or something. Okay, now that's interesting because אפוטרופוס apotropus sometimes
is invested with the power of שליח, shaliach, but nevertheless אתם ולא
התורם תרומת חבירו atem v'lo hatoreim t'rumat chaveiro or just סתם, stam,
somebody is taking stuff that isn't his. In any of these cases,
right, it has to be either you or your שליח. shaliach. So
אתם atem is coming to exclude people that are connected to you.
So I might have thought אם אתם ולא שלוחכם, im atem v'lo
shluchachem, I might have thought if you're excluding those people, maybe you
exclude a שליח shaliach as well. נמי קא משמע לן nami kamashma
lan that we're not excluding a שליח. shaliach. So again the question
is you could learn out שליחות shlichus from קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
and from גירושין. Geirushin. Why do you need גם אתם gam atem
to include a שליח shaliach by תרומה? Terumah? And so there are
two answers. The first answer was it's not to include a שליח,
shaliach, it's to tell you if you're going to have a שליח,
shaliach, the שליח shaliach has to be like you, the שליח shaliach
has to be Jewish, okay? And answer number two is you might
have thought to exclude שליח shaliach because of the emphasis of אתם,
atem, so גם gam tells you that a שליח shaliach works here
as well. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this:
הניחא לרבי יהושע בן קרחה אלא לרבי יונתן דמפיק ליה להאי קרא
לדרשה אחרינא מנלן? Ha nicha l'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha ela l'Rabbi Yonatan
d'mafik lei l'hai kra l'drasha achrina minalan? That's good for רבי יהושע
בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha that uses it to learn out
all those laws. About,
according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, I'm sorry, that's good for רבי
יהושע בן קרחה, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha, excuse me, that uses the
פסוק pasuk by קרבן פסח Korban Pesach right to tell me that
one person can represent the group and there can be a שליח
shaliach by קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Okay, but according to
רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonatan that uses the פסוק pasuk of קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach to tell me a different law, מנלן? minalan? Where do
I know that there could be an idea of שליחות? shlichus? Because
I won't know it from קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. דתניא, d'tanya, we
taught in the ברייתא. Baraisa. רבי יונתן אומר מנין שכל ישראל כולן
יוצאין בפסח אחד? Rabbi Yonatan omer: minalan shekol Yisrael kulan yotzin b'Pesach
echad?
How do I know that in theory all the Jewish people can
have one קרבן פסח? Korban Pesach? Sort of like you know sometimes
we have the same idea
by a סוכה. sukkah. And it's used to prove the idea that
you can be יוצא yotzei with a borrowed סוכה. sukkah. Because they
learn from a פסוק pasuk that all the Jewish people could sit
in one סוכה. sukkah. So if it can't be possible that everybody
has an ownership of that סוכה sukkah that's worth a פרוטה perutah
the way רש״י Rashi says it, so it proves to you that
you can be יוצא yotzei in a borrowed סוכה. sukkah. So there's
a similar argument here. How do you know everybody can be יוצא
yotzei with one קרבן פסח? Korban Pesach? The problem is if everybody's
יוצא yotzei with one קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, unless it's a sheep
the size of the לויתן Leviathan or something, right, talking about סוכות,
sukkos,
not everybody will get a כזית. kezayis. So he's using this to
prove, רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonatan uses this to prove that a קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach you don't have to eat it to be יוצא.
yotzei. Now that's normally not the approach. The normal approach is if
you're not able to eat a כזית, kezayis, you're not יוצא, yotzei,
because as distinct from all other קרבנות, korbanot, all other קרבנות korbanot
are brought for the sake of offering them up on the מזבח.
mizbeach. The eating is just like a derivative type of a purpose.
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach the whole reason it's brought is in order
to eat it that night. And here's an interesting way that you
can see that. If it's brought בטומאה, b'tumah, most of כלל ישראל
Klal Yisrael is טמא מת tamei meis or whatever and you're going
to bring a קרבן פסח בטומאה. Korban Pesach b'tumah. Welcome, welcome. Then
what would you eat it בטומאה? b'tumah? So the normal הלכה halacha
is that when another קרבן korban is brought בטומאה, b'tumah, okay, it
would not be eaten בטומאה b'tumah because basically the טומאה tumah is
only overridden for the sake of doing what's necessary to be done
with the קרבן. korban. So you would bring it בטומאה b'tumah but
you wouldn't eat it with טומאה. tumah. The one exception is קרבן
פסח. Korban Pesach. קרבן פסח Korban Pesach if it's brought בטומאה b'tumah
is eaten בטומאה b'tumah because its whole purpose is to be eaten.
Okay, so that's the normal approach. But רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonatan disagrees.
And he says in theory there could be one little sheep for
all of כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, okay,
and therefore you don't have to eat a כזית kezayis to be
יוצא yotzei your קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So
מנלן שכל ישראל יוצאין בפסח אחד, minalan shekol Yisrael yotzin b'Pesach echad,
top of מב עמוד א. mem-bet amud aleph. Okay, שנאמר shenemar the
פסוק pasuk says ושחטו אתו כל קהל עדת ישראל בין הערבים. v'shachatu
oto kol kehal adat Yisrael bein ha'arbayim. That they should all slaughter
it.
But do they all
slaughter? One person. אלא מכאן שכל ישראל יוצאין בפסח אחד. Ella mikan
shekol Yisrael yotzin b'Pesach echad. You see that everybody is יוצא yotzei
with one קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So for him it proves that
you don't need a כזית kezayis for every individual. But says the
גמרא, Gemara, if that's what you're using the פסוק pasuk to prove,
you don't have the concept of שליחות shlichus by קרבן פסח. Korban
Pesach. So שליח דקדש מנליה? shaliach dikdash minalei? Now you could say
well we know it by תרומה, Terumah, we know it by גיטין,
Gittin, but as the גמרא Gemara says קדשא, Kodsha, a קרבן korban
is the highest level, is the most strict. So if you don't
have it by קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, how do you know that
there's an idea of שליחות, shlichus, of agency, that applies to קדשים?
kodashim? found out. So the גמרא gemara says מנא ליה, minalei, it
says מיניה. minei. You learn it from that case itself. Meaning, even
if the point of the פסוק posuk is to tell you that
you don't need to eat a כזית kezayis to be יוצא yotzei
the קרבן פסח, korban pesach, it describes a scenario where all of
ישראל yisrael own one little sheep and one person is שחט'ינג shechting
it. So that's שליחות. shlichus. One person is שחט'ינג shechting it for
everybody. So you don't need to say the purpose of the פסוק
posuk is to teach you that, still that's the scenario it's describing.
So that teaches you the concept of שליחות. shlichus. So the גמרא
gemara says no, ודילמא שאני התם דאיתא שותפות בגווייהו. vidilma shani hatom
de'isay shutfus begavaihu.
You can't learn from that. If everybody is co-owners of the קרבן
פסח, korban pesach, then because of their direct connection to the קרבן,
korban, one of the owners can שחט shecht it on behalf of
everybody else. But everybody has already something that's very concretely makes them
all part of the same enterprise and makes this person representing the
group because they're all partners in that group. That's very different than
if you're unrelated to me, we have no shared interests or whatever,
and I just say hey, you be my שליח, shliach, you go
and do so and so.
So the כהן גדול kohen gadol on יום כיפור yom kippur is
a bad example because it's the כהן גדול kohen gadol and it's
specific...
well, no, because again, as I've been saying, the reason we don't
bring the proof from just קדשים kodshim in general, what כהנים kohanim
do stuff for us, I mean the גמרא gemara asks the question
is כהנים kohanim שלוחא דרחמנא, shluchei derachmana, שלוחא דידן, shluchei didan, but
there's no proof by the things that the כהן kohen does that
we're supposed to be doing it. Maybe what the תורה torah is
saying is your job is to bring it to the כהנים, kohanim,
the כהנים's kohanim job is to sprinkle it and do what he
does. Where do you see that he's your agent? Right? You do
your job, he does his job. But by קרבן פסח, korban pesach,
it says you're supposed to שחט shecht it. משכו וקחו לכם צאן
למשפחותיכם, mishchu u'kechu lachem tzon l'mishpichoseichem, right, ושחטו אותו, v'shachatu oso, well
that's כל קהל עדת ישראל, kol kehal adas yisrael, but you're supposed
to שחט shecht it and you're not שחט'ינג shechting it, one person
is שחט'ינג shechting it for the group. So that's a חידוש chidush
of שליח. shliach. But the גמרא gemara says but maybe you can't
generalize from that. Because maybe there he's not just a random person
who's your agent. You all are part of the same enterprise, you
all have a financial investment in this sheep and ownership of this
sheep, so of course he can represent the group. That doesn't prove
normal שליחות. shlichus. So I just want to say two things about
this. First of all, okay,
so תוספות tosafos asks the obvious question: why didn't the גמרא gemara
ask this on the previous דף daf where it used the example
of קרבן פסח? korban pesach? Right? There it was happy that קרבן
פסח, korban pesach, the idea of one person שחט'ינג shechting was a
proof of agency. Why here does it say oh maybe it's different
because of ownership? So תוספות tosafos says no, because on the previous
דף daf
we weren't saying that all of ישראל yisrael owned one קרבן. korban.
We were saying one person שחט'ס shechts for all of ישראל. yisrael.
What does that mean? It means all... everybody brings their קרבן, korban,
every group brings their קרבן, korban, and you've got one person שחט'ינג
shechting for every group. You bring me your קרבן korban I'll שחט
shecht it, you bring me your קרבן korban I'll שחט shecht it.
So in that case if you describe the scenario of ושחטו אותו
כל קהל עדת ישראל בין הערביים, v'shachatu oso kol kehal adas yisrael
bein ha'arbayim,
one person שחט'ס shechts for everybody means I... there's one designated שוחט
shechter for every group that brings their קרבן פסח, korban pesach, that
proves an idea of שליחות, shlichus, of agency, even when you don't
have a financial ownership, right, a financial stake. Whereas here we're saying
כל קהל עדת ישראל kol kehal adas yisrael means they all own
the same sheep. If they all own the same sheep, it's not
such a big חידוש chidush of שליחות, shlichus, because they're all part-owners,
so of course you can represent the group. So the other thing
I want to say about this is that this idea about the
different way of thinking about what agency is, you know, I think
I've mentioned this multiple times before, the רב rav speaks about this
a great deal in two scenarios in הלכה. halacha. The most... the
biggest example is תפילה בציבור, tefilla b'tzibbur, but he also talks about
it by זימון, zimmun, where he says, you know, by those places,
it's not like we... you know, although the guy is actually called
שליח ציבור, shliach tzibbur, by the way, here's an interesting little fun
fact as my kids would say, the only place in all of
the משנה mishna where it says שלוחו של אדם כמותו, shlucho shel
adam k'moso, a person's agent is like him, is the משנה mishna
in ברכות berachos talking about a שליח ציבור. shliach tzibbur. So it's
interesting thinking about the שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur models of agency. So
the problem is with a שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur is that the
גמרא gemara says that you have to pray for yourself, you can't
have somebody else pray for you. Like let's say I'm you're just
דאוונינג, davening, you go to another person and just say you just
say your שמנה עשרה, shemoneh esrei, I'll stand here and listen and
say אמן. amen. Are you יוצא? yotzei? So according to, you know,
many שיטות shittos the answer is no, you're not, you have to
דאוון daven for yourself. So how does the whole institution of שליח
ציבור shliach tzibbur work, which is for people who didn't know how
to דאוון daven and for the illiterate? How were they יוצא? yotzei?
So the רב rav said no, no, there what's happening is not
that he is sort of, you know, discharging for you your personal
obligation and that he is your personal agent and his תפילה tefilla
is your תפילה. tefilla. That's not what's happening. What's happening is you
have the entire sort of community, right, as a corporate entity and
it is
the... And whatever. And that entity is represented by the שליח.
shaliach. He is the mouthpiece for that communal entity. But he is
not the individual representative of each individual. He says that's the difference
of your silent שמנה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei and your petition of שמנה
עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. Your silent שמנה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei is תפילה בציבור.
tefila b'tzibbur. You're praying as an individual in the presence of a
ציבור. tzibbur. The repetition of the שמנה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei is תפילת
הציבור. tefilat ha-tzibbur. You're no longer praying as an individual. The entire
community as one unit is praying to God through the mouthpiece of
the שליח ציבור. shaliach tzibbur. So that by the way is an
interesting sort of model you see is the גמרא's Gemara point of
אית ליה שותפי בגווייהו. islei shutfei begavaihu. If we all own this
sheep and that's the whole פשט pshat of the תורה Torah that
שה לבית אבות se la-veit avot that there's one household that owns
the sheep. So when this one guy שחט, shechts, who has to
see him as he's doing my obligation, I'm really supposed to be
the one that's שוחט. shechting. No, you're all one unit, one household,
everybody has shared ownership in the sheep, and one person, you know,
represents the שחיטה shechita of the entire unit as a unit. Okay,
and that's what the גמרא Gemara says. That's very different than when
there's no shared ownership and so on and you're just having a
person who's representing you individually. Okay, so you cannot learn out from
קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אלא
מהכא ela me-hacha rather from here: ויקחו להם איש שה לבית אבות
שה לבית. veyikchu lahem ish se la-veit avot se la-bayit. Okay, so
now not about the שחיטה shechting of the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach,
but the purchasing of the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. That one person
should take it, so presumably he's taking it on behalf of everyone,
so the and before it's taken they don't yet have a joint
ownership, right? Their joint ownership only comes after it's purchased on behalf
of everyone. Okay, so he takes it for everyone so he's their
שליח. shaliach. So the גמרא Gemara says no: ודילמא התם נמי דאית
ליה שותפי בגווייהו. vedilma hatam nami de-islei shutfei begavaihu. Presumably saying yeah,
but you know nevertheless that's part of creating this sense, maybe they
all gave him the money to purchase it. It's all in the
end of the day, they're all going to be shared owner of
it. At the end of the day they're part of the same
enterprise and that's very different than I take a random person and
say, 'Here, here's a גט, get, go divorce my wife.' Right? There's
nothing that brings us together and that makes that us sort of
you know him as a representative of the whole. Here there's a
group and he's a representative of the group. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says so we still don't know where you have agency by
קדשים. kodashim. So the גמרא Gemara says no: אם כן תרי קראי
למה לי. im ken trei kraei lamma li. No, you're right, but
then you wouldn't need two פסוקים. psukim. You wouldn't need one פסוק
pasuk that describes שחיטה shechting on behalf of the group and one
פסוק pasuk that describes purchasing on behalf of the group. You wouldn't
have to say it twice. So by saying it twice, ממיבעי ליה
להיכא דשייך. mimmibi'ei lei le-heicha de-shayach. If you don't need it to
tell you there's an idea of agency when somebody has a sort
of already a connection to what's going on, תמיה ליה להיכא דלא
שייך. temiyei lei le-heicha de-la shayach. The extra time, once it says
by שחיטה shechting and once by purchasing, at least one of those
should be used, it's extra, to teach you that you can be
an agent even when you have no direct connection to what's going
on. So the גמרא Gemara says no, כי דהכי, ki dehachi, can't
use it for that. We need the idea of purchasing the פסח
Pesach to tell me something else. The גמרא Gemara says הא מבעי
ליה לכדרבי יצחק ha miba'ei lei le-kiderabbi yitzchak you need it for
רבי יצחק, Rabbi Yitzchak, דאמר רבי יצחק: de-amar rabbi yitzchak: איש זוכה
ולא קטן זוכה. ish zocheh ve-lo koton zocheh. No, it's ויקחו להם
איש שה לבית אבות. veyikchu lahem ish se la-veit avot. Only a
man can purchase; a minor is not yet able to take possession
of something in general, not just by קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So
that's what the פסוק pasuk is telling me, not the idea that
somebody does it on behalf of others. Wait one minute, so the
גמרא Gemara says no: ההוא מאיש לפי אכלו נפקא. hahu me-ish le-phi
achlo nafka. That we should learn out from איש לפי אכלו, ish
le-phi achlo, each person, each man according to their ability they'll be
able to eat and not a minor because a minor does not
have a shared ownership because a minor cannot take possession and be
an owner. Okay, so we already know from another איש ish that
it can't be a minor. So what do you need the פסוק
pasuk that says ויקחו להם איש שה לבית אבות? veyikchu lahem ish
se la-veit avot? One person takes on behalf of everyone. You don't
need to exclude a minor. What that's doing is it's extra and
telling you this idea of agency. Yes, well wait minute, let's just
also point out another interesting thing about תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot says
איש זוכה ואין קטן זוכה. ish zocheh ve-en koton zocheh. If you
look at תוספות Tosafot it says: ואם תאמר ולמה לי קרא והקיימא
לן דאין יד לקטן. ve-im tomar ve-lammi kra ve-kayma lan de-ein yad
le-koton. Why need a פסוק? pasuk? In general I know that a
minor does not cannot you know cannot take possession of things. Why
do I need a פסוק pasuk here by קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
to tell it to me? יש אומרים דגבי פסח איצטריך. yesh omrim
de-gabe pesach itzterich. No, because by פסח Pesach I might have thought
it was different. סלקא דעתך הואיל דשייך באכילת פסחים. salka da'atach ho'il
de-shayach ba-achilat pesachim. וצריך לימנות עליו. ve-tzarich limannot alav. That a קטן
koton can eat from the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Okay, if a
if a קטן koton wants to participate in the קרבן פסח. Korban
Pesach. Interesting, right? Like I said, perfect דף daf for today. שחיטת
shechitat קרבן פסח Korban Pesach was done today, eating tonight is a
סדר Seder where obviously a major center is the minor, is the
children, the קטנים. ktanim. Okay, and they actually could. be part of
eating the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. They would have to participate in
the group, they would have to like sign me up, I'm going
to sign up for this group, להימנות עליו, leihimanot alav, okay, they
would have to be counted as part of the group. So and
if you're not part of the group you can't eat, whether you're
an adult or a minor. Okay, but minors would be able to
eat if they would sign up to be part of the group.
Okay, דכתיב שה לבית אבות dechativ seh l'veit avot so אפילו קטן
afilu katan לבית l'vayit excuse me a household including a minor. אימא
אף לכם זכה eima af lachem zachah קמשמע לן. kamashma lan. So
I might think that, you know, that if a minor therefore can
be part of the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, can eat if he
signs up to the group, so then maybe by קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach I can be זוכה zocheh for קטן. katan. So what you'd
say well what difference does it make? If he can be part
of the
group
without
owning it, why would it matter? Well, I don't know, let's say
a minor
asks me to go purchase a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach for the
minor's
group, not for
you know he's not part of my group, right?
So anyway,
I'm
not able to
do
that.
So what so it's interesting, A, I just
you know
because it's just סתם stam interesting that even though a minor doesn't
have ownership, he
can still be part of the
קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach if
he signs
up
to the group and he can actually eat from
the
קרבן
פסח.
Korban
Pesach.
Again you know interesting if you think about just
the idea of you know the focus on minors in the סדר
Seder
and so on. Okay but nevertheless he cannot be זוכה. zocheh. Okay,
I
can't take possession of
something
for a minor and that's what I
learn out from the פסוק pasuk of you know or he can't
be
זוכה zocheh excuse me I think I did it in the reverse
way.
I'm sorry no
no
I did the reverse way excuse me. איש
ואכלו להם
איש ish v'ichlu lahem ish he cannot take possession for
others. I'm sorry I
reversed it. Okay
so he can be part of another person's קרבן
פסח
Korban
Pesach
but he cannot take possession
for others and that's what I learn out
from the פסוק
pasuk
of איש. ish. Yes, you
had a question?
But the גמרא Gemara says ההוא מאיש לפי אכלו נפקא.
hahu me'ish lefi ochlo nafka. Yeah. Why is this on
what basis does the סתם stam privilege the לימוד limmud of איש
זוכה ולא קטן זוכה ish zocheh v'lo katan zocheh rather than use
that original פסוק pasuk for שליחות? shlichut? Because it's the only argument
that you could use it for שליחות shlichut was that you were
saying that it was superfluous. But if I can show you it's
not superfluous, you have no argument because the simple sense of the
פסוק pasuk does not tell you שליחות shlichut because as the גמרא
Gemara said it's a special case. It's a case where you have
a שייכות shayichut where you are connected. How do you use that
פסוק pasuk to teach me שליחות shlichut for a case where you're
not connected? So in a general logic of no you can't use
the פסוק pasuk for this, it's really used for that, often the
privileged לימוד limmud is more direct and not simply... Right, because the
לימוד limmud here, right, if the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk
would have been שליחות, shlichut, the גמרא Gemara wouldn't have disqualified it
because there's another דרשה derashah there. But the פשט pshat of the
פסוק pasuk doesn't tell you general שליחות shlichut because it's a special
case here because you have an ownership. So therefore the only basis
to use it for general שליחות shlichut is that it's superfluous. But
it's not superfluous because it's telling me something of פשט. pshat. Okay,
so from איש לפי אכלו ish lefi ochlo I learn the idea
yeah just just repeat because I said it wrong the first time,
from איש לפי אכלו ish lefi ochlo I learn the idea that
a קטן katan can take only an adult can take possession of
the פסח Pesach for others, a קטן katan cannot take possession of
the פסח Pesach for others as תוספות Tosafot says although a קטן
katan can be part of the פסח Pesach that an adult took
and sign up for it, but the only an adult can take
the פסח Pesach on behalf of others. Okay, but nevertheless and that
I learn from איש לפי אכלו. ish lefi ochlo. So ויקחו להם
איש שה לבית אבות v'yikchu lahem ish seh l'veit avot is seen
as superfluous and because that's superfluous that teaches me the idea of
שליחות shlichut by קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Even in a case or
by קדשים, kodashim, even in a case when somebody does not have
joint ownership or is not directly connected. Okay so now the גמרא
Gemara continues like this. דאמר רב גידל אמר רב מנין ששלוחו של
אדם כמותו. d'amar Rav Gidel amar Rav minayin sheshlucho shel adam k'moto.
Now okay so now we're done for now. We we basically have
what are our לימודים? limmudim? Okay we have קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach.
Okay and we have what do you call it? We've got גירושין
gerushin and we also learn out קידושין. kiddushin. Okay there we say
there we learn out this from ושלחה v'shilchah and this from ושחטו
אותו v'shachatu oto or it's learned out from ויקחו להם איש. v'yikchu
lahem ish. Basically the idea one person is shechting, one person is
purchasing. Those two tell you the idea of שליחות. shlichut. They're not
they don't they're not limited because they covered separate areas. This covers
קדשים, kodashim, right? And this covers חולין. chullin. This Venn diagram... I
well this but this is where they're not intersecting. It's the תרומה
terumah that intersects. תרומה's terumah the thing that intersects because תרומה terumah
has an element of קדשים kodashim here. Okay anyway whatever, but but
the point is so you can't learn out from תרומה terumah because
it intersects. So you can learn out from these because they don't
intersect. Okay this is מעשר, ma'aser, this is מחשבה, machshavah, okay anyway
this is רוב מעשה על ידי שליח, rov ma'aseh al yedei shliach,
okay anyway okay anyway these are things that they have that the
other one don't have so it can't be because of any unique
shared characteristics. So this tells you So this tells you it's the
whole world, that there's this idea of שליחות, shlichus, okay? We learn
it out from those two things. From תרומה, terumah, גם אתם. gam
atem. Where do we learn out from? Either from the אתם atem
part we learn out that it has to be like you, so
a שליח shaliach has to be a Jew, okay? We know he
has to be בתורת, be-toras, the laws have to apply to him,
but there are cases where the laws might apply to him even
if he's, even if he's not Jewish. So אתם atem tells you
a שליח shaliach has to be a Jew, and גם gam tells
you that there is a שליח shaliach because you shouldn't come to
say that maybe it has to be, since אתם atem says, you
know, not sharecroppers, etc., right? It has to be you and not
sharecroppers, etc., so therefore I might say maybe a שליח shaliach doesn't
work, so גם gam tells you no, no, a שליח shaliach works
here as well. But basically, the general sense of שליחות shlichus I
learn from these two, okay? Can you learn it out from just
shechting קרבן פסח? korban pesach? No, maybe this is special, shechting and
purchasing a קרבן פסח korban pesach in general, because there everybody is
joint owners. That doesn't tell you a general idea of having a
stranger as my שליח. shaliach. And joint owners, as I say, creates
a sense of like a corporate identity, a unit that one person
represents the group, is very different than an idea of a personal
agent and a שליח shaliach that is not really deeply connected to
me. Okay, so that's why I needed to sort of use an
extra פסוק pasuk to expand that beyond a case of joint owners.
Okay. So all this is שליחות shlichus באיסורא b'issura not בממונא? b'mammona?
No, well, we mean we haven't done ממונא. mammona. It's a good
point, and you know, I sort of been assuming that that's been
included, but, you know. But at ממונא mammona you can't have a
non-Jew be your שליח. shaliach. Well, that's true, the exclusion of non-Jews
includes דיני ממונות dinei mammonos as well. But it is true that
so far the areas the גמרא gemara have been looking at are
more like איסור והיתר issur v'heter areas and then ממונא. mammona. Let's
take a look because we're about to turn to the ממונא mammona
issue. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says like this. Alright. Okay. ולהא
דאמר רב גידל אמר רב u'leha d'amar Rav Gidel amar Rav מניין
ששלוחו של אדם כמותו minayin she'shlucho shel adam k'moso שנאמר ונשיא אחד
נשיא אחד she'ne'emar v'nasi echad nasi echad. ממטה, that here you learn
out by the division of the land of Israel, that it says
there was one prince from each tribe, and that prince made the,
you know, was sort of part of the division and maybe, you
know, represented the entire tribe in whatever negotiations there had to be
about how you divided, although in the end it gets done through
lots and the אורים ותומים urim v'tumim and other types of ways.
But nevertheless, to the degree you needed the person to participate, he
was represented by the נשיא. nasi. Okay. So the גמרא gemara says,
ותיפוק ליה שליחות מהכא, v'teifok lei shlichus me'hacha, why do you learn
out from that פסוק? pasuk? Why not learn out from all these
places? So you see the גמרא gemara is assuming that the discussion
of שליחות shlichus relates to the whole range, including דיני ממונות. dinei
mammonos. Okay. So the גמרא gemara says, no, ותסברא, v'tisabra, wait, do
you really think that makes sense? That that פסוק pasuk there by
the division of Israel is really the basis for שליחות? shlichus? דשליחות
היא? d'shlichus hi? Is that what you think that's really שליחות? shlichus?
והא קטנים לאו בני שליחות נינהו, v'ha katanim lav bnei shlichus nin'hu,
there were minors, right, that were part of, you know, there was
the whole age range is represented in the division of the land
and they can't have an agent work for them. אלא... ela... that
a minor cannot have an agent work for him. Unborn children were
also. We're going to get to unborn children. So what's your question?
Why do you say the minors are included in the... How do
you know they were included in the division of the land? Because
they were. Because let's imagine that you had, I don't know, let's
say some kids were orphans and right, their father had died and
they get on their own behalf a portion in the land at
the time. Yes. Why? I mean, what do you think? They'd be
landless? I mean, right? Everybody... Okay, that's taken for granted. Alright. אלא
כי הא דרבא בר רב הונא דאמר רבא בר רב הונא אמר
רב גידל אמר רב מניין שזכין לאדם שלא בפניו. ela ki ha
d'Rabba bar Rav Huna d'amar Rabba bar Rav Huna amar Rav Gidel
amar Rav minayin she'zachin l'adam shelo b'fanav. How do you know that
you can take possession of something for a person on their behalf
not in their presence? שנאמר she'ne'emar ונשיא אחד נשיא nasi אחד. Here,
they are taking possession for everybody's portion for their behalf, but that's
not necessarily an idea of שליחות. shlichus. Now that's interesting because there's
other גמרות gemaros that discuss why there's זכייה zechiyah מטעם שליחות mitam
shlichus or not מטעם שליחות. mitam shlichus. Okay, this גמרא gemara is
sort of saying, well, זכייה zechiyah can't be based on שליחות shlichus
because then it wouldn't work for a minor. And we start with
a presumption that you cannot be the agent and the representative of
a minor. So but you can take possession of something for somebody
either not in their presence and not only that, even if they're
a minor. A minor's considered not in their presence. Meaning, if it's
just that I can take possession of something for you not in
your presence when it's on your behalf, we could say that's שליחות,
shlichus, but you are presumed to want me to be your שליח
shaliach because it's all for your benefit even though it's not in
your presence. But when it's a minor, you can't be, the minor
is presumed to make this person a שליח. shaliach. Fundamentally, there's no
שליחות shlichus by minors. And therefore, this shows that זכין, zachin, at
least should show that זכין zachin is... Even if you, even in
גירות, geirus, even in גירות, geirus, yeah, we're not talking about גירות.
geirus. Anyway, but it just is basically the principle that you can
do something, you know, you can take possession of something for somebody
or act on behalf of somebody in their behalf, not separate from
an idea of being seen as a representative of their of that
person. So anyway, so that's what we learn out from this and
it is not teaching you a general idea of שליחות, shlichus, it's
teaching you an idea of זוכין zochin which in one way is
more limited, it's only when something is black and white to somebody's
in somebody's benefit, but on the other hand it's more expansive, you
don't need to be appointed and you can do it even for
a minor. That's what we learn out here but not a general
idea of שליחות. shlichus. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says שנאמר shene'emar
okay so the גמרא Gemara says ותסברה v'tisbora one minute does that
make sense that that's considered זוכין zochin which I just described as
black and white for somebody's benefit? זכות הוא לו? zechus hu lo?
He, how do you know that that's the person's benefit? חובה נמי
איכא. hachova nami ika. Maybe when that נשיא nasi took possession for
the minors that were part of his tribe, maybe it was to
their detriment? דאיכא דניחא ליה בהר ולא ניחא ליה בבקעה, de'ika de'nicha
lei behar v'lo nicha lei be'vika, ואיכא דניחא ליה בבקעה ולא ניחא
ליה בהר. v'ika de'nicha lei be'vika v'lo nicha lei behar. He's going
to divide up you know which section everybody gets and maybe these
minors would have rather have had you know the the mountain and
those minors would have rather have had the valley? So you know
it's not just otherwise you would have got nothing now you're getting
something. You're determining which portion I'm getting. So that's not all black
and white in my benefit, there's a lot of judgment here. Okay
so why can you do that on behalf of the minor? So
that's not your normal זוכין. zochin. So the גמרא Gemara says דאלא
כדירב בר רפונא דאמר רב בר רפונא אמר רב גידל אמר רב,
d'ela k'dirav bar rafuna d'amar rav bar rafuna amar rav giddel amar
rav, you're right, it doesn't teach you a general principle of זוכין.
zochin. A general principle of זוכין zochin you wouldn't learn from there
that has to be a special case because that's a case where
there's actually tradeoffs and it's not all black and white. So if
that's true that's not the general principle of זוכין, zochin, what principle
is it? So it's the following principle: מניין ליתומים שבאו לחלוק בנכסי
אביהן, minayin l'yisomim she'bau lachlok b'nichsei avihen, how do you know when
orphans presumably minors are coming to divide their father's estate, שבבית דין
מעמידין להם אפוטרופוס לחוב ולזכות, she'bezdin mamidin lahem apitropas l'chov u'lizkos, that
the בית דין bezdin can appoint a a guardian right or you
know some type of a court-appointed overseer in order to to for
their detriment and for their benefit. So the גמרא Gemara just interrupts
for a minute. The גמרא Gemara says לחובה מאי, l'chova mai, why
would they have why would they appoint a guardian for their detriment?
No, no, no, what it means is אלא לחוב על מנת לזכות,
ela l'chov al m'nas l'izkos, that for the purpose of benefiting them
they're going to appoint somebody that's going to be authorized even if
it leads to some negatives. Okay now there are different scenarios of
negatives. One negative is like the person actually made a mistake. Okay
we'll sort of get to something like that in a minute. But
another scenario of a negative is I'm sorry this was the judgment
I made that this field would be good for you even though
it meant giving up that field and you can't come and complain
oh well I never would have wanted to have lost that. My
whole job was to make judgment calls and to make tradeoffs meaning
לחוב ולזכות l'chov u'lizkos means to make the types of tradeoffs that
are necessary to get to some fair distribution. So how do you
know which is exactly our question? It's not classic זוכין. zochin. Classic
זוכין zochin is here's a present for somebody, great I'll take possession
of it, it's all good. Okay here it's tradeoffs. How do you
know that in the special case of orphans coming to divide their
father's estate, minors, that you can actually appoint someone to make the
division with the tradeoffs that it's part is part of that process?
תלמוד לומר ונשיא אחד נשיא אחד ממטה תקחו. talmud lomar v'nasi echad
nasi echad mi'mate tiku. That's what you had by the division of
the land of ישראל. Israel. Okay so that is not a number
one general שליחות shlichus because it's קטנים. ktanim. It's not a general
זוכין zochin because there are tradeoffs. It's a special authority that is
given by now what's special about it? What allows that case to
be special? Is it because it's about like some type of a
division of some inheritance? Does that make it special because that's obviously
a similar idea to the what happened in ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael?
Right this was sort of the tribes' נחלה, nachala, we were all
inheriting it and now we had to divide it. Is that what
made it special or is what made it special that allowed you
to be authorized to do tradeoffs that you were appointed by the
court? And that is that seems to be the way the ראשונים
rishonim go, it was the fact the court appoints you that gives
you special authority. And obviously the parallel by by ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael was well God appointed you, right? God said there's going to
be a נשיא there that's going to divide so you see that
from there we learn a model that at least a court-appointed you
know representative
trustee can have the power to make these types of tradeoff for
on behalf of the people that he is made the trustee of.
But it's not part of the general principle of שליחות, shlichus, it's
not even part of the general principle of
זוכין.
zochin. Yes. פשיטא, peshita, a trustee has to make this kind of
decision otherwise he's not really...
obviously, right correct, and that's actually let's take a look because now
we're going to spend a little time on this. אלא רב נחמן
אמר שמואל יתומים שבאו לחלוק בנכסי אביהן בית דין מעמידין להם אפוטרופוס
ובוררים להם חלק יפה. ella rav nachman amar shmuel yisomim she'bau lachlok
b'nichsei avihen bezdin mamidin lahem apitropas u'vorim lahem chelek yafe. If minors
come to divide their father's estate, a בית דין bezdin will appoint
for them a guardian and choose for them a good portion. אפוטרופוס
apitropis and they will choose out for them a good portion, meaning
each one will try to sort of determine like the best division,
okay.
So,
so רש"י Rashi says לכל אחד יפה לזה ויפה לזה. lechol echad
yafeh lazeh veyafeh lazeh. They try to do, you know, give the
best, you know, to do good by everybody. Of course, another way
to understand this, right, is, you know, I think there's a question
here of the גרסא. girsa.
Anyway, no, but anyway, but the question is, one minute, no.
Okay, no, it's something else. Anyway, okay, let's keep on going. Because
you could imagine a different system. You could imagine a system that
each minor gets an אפוטרופוס apitropis and each אפוטרופוס apitropis fights for
the interests of his minor, of his, you know, representee,
represent-like representee, right? So therefore by each one being an advocate for
the person they're representing, that will lead to the fairest position, right?
As opposed to the way that this sounds like you have one
representative, one trustee, who tries to be fair and equal distribution to
everybody that he is entrust-that is under his charge. Okay. So ובוררין
להם חלק יפה. uvorim lahem chelek yafeh. והגדילו, vehigdilo, but let's say
now that they've grown up, יכולים למחות. yecholim limchos. They can protest.
And they can say, you know, I'm not happy with the portion
that you gave to me. I want to do a re-division of
the assets. Of course, just imagine how disastrous that would be in
terms of trying to like, you know, here they are, they're twelve
years, you know, a whole group of them, you divide up the
estate so everybody can get on with their lives and ten years
later, one of them now becomes בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah and he
wants to reverse the whole division. Oh, I don't like the portion
you got for me. Okay. So that's where רב נחמן Rav Nachman
comes in. The גמרא Gemara says רב נחמן דידיה אמר, Rav Nachman
didey amar, Rav Nachman in his own name says, אם הגדילו אינם
יכולים למחות. im higdilu einam yecholim limchos. No, they cannot protest after
they've grown up, דאם כן מה כח בית דין יפה. de'im kein
mah koach beis din yafeh. Because if you don't say that, where's
the power of בית דין? beis din? Right? The whole thing is
that they've been appointed by בית דין beis din and the authority
of בית דין, beis din, meaning A, it's just practically would undermine,
you know, would be counterproductive at the societal level. But he's also
saying like it makes a mockery of בית דין's beis din's what
it means to be a court appointee if I've been given the
authority of the court and then that can be reversed ten years
later. No. If you're backed by the authority of the court, that
means even if the minors don't like it when they grow up,
it's still binding. Now by the way, the principle of that you
could be מוחה mocheh is relevant in a normal case of זכיה.
zchiya. Okay. The example I've used in the past is, you know,
Dov is wants to get rid of his old Ferrari, it's two
years old, he's planning to trade it in. So he loves דף
יומי Daf Yomi so much that he's going to give it over
there to David to take possession for me because I'm not around.
Okay. So he gives David the car keys, he's now זוכה לאדם,
zocheh leadam, he's taken possession for me. Now David comes and says
Rabbi Linzer, here's this gift Dov that gave me. I say what?
Me? I don't want gifts. I do it all לשמה. lishma. שונא
מתנות יחיה, sonei matanos yichyeh, חס ושלום. chas veshalom. Okay.
So now at that stage, it's not like I own it and
I have to be מפקיר mafkir it. You did it on my
behalf. Once I'm brought into the equation and I make it clear
that that was not on my behalf, I wouldn't have wanted it,
it doesn't work. Okay, that's what מחאה macha'ah is. You did a
זכיה שלא בפניו zchiya shelo befanav on the presumption that it was
on my behalf, then you inform me of it and I say
that wasn't on my behalf. By the way, that also works. Dov
mentioned before the issue about זכיה zchiyah by גירות geirus of a
קטן, katan, when you're מגייר megayer somebody who's an who's a minor,
okay, and then the person becomes בר/בת מצוה, Bar/Bas Mitzvah, now they're
an adult, they can actually say at that age, you know what,
I don't want to be Jewish. And you only did this because
you were representing my interests, but I don't want to be Jewish
and retroactively they're not Jewish, the גירות geirus doesn't work. So once
somebody is now present,
either they were just physically distant or they're now an adult, they
can actually say you were not operating on my behalf. So רב
נחמן Rav Nachman says you can't say that when it was a
court-appointed trustee. A, because it'll be disastrous in terms of practical, but
also B, because it undermines the authority of the court. The authority
of the court is great enough that it overrides even a future
objection. Okay. But now the גמרא Gemara says one minute. So the
גמרא Gemara says ומי אית ליה לרב נחמן דאם כן מה כח
בית דין יפה? umi is lei l'Rav Nachman de'im kein mah koach
beis din yafeh? So does רב נחמן Rav Nachman really hold that?
That like you can't override a court, a court's of-like you know,
that we're concerned about the power and authority of the court and
we won't let it be overridden later? והתנן, vehatnan, we've learned in
the משנה, Mishnah, שום הדינים shum hadayanim שפיחתו שתות או הותירו שתות.
shepichasu shtus o hosiru shtus.
Let's say the court has to come and assess the value of
property to allow a creditor to seize property not in the presence
of the debtor. The debtor is off and he's run away, and
I want to take possession of his property, and the court will
now assess the value and I'll take possession of his property. Let's
say their assessed value was greater or less than a sixth of
the actual value of the property. Now that's a normal amount that
under normal circumstances, if it was a normal transaction, would be a
big enough discrepancy that the sale would be בטל. batel. Okay, so
if I overpaid you or underpaid you more than a sixth, the
sale is בטל. batel. Let's say the court's assessment, okay, שפיחתו שתות
או הותירו שתות shepichasu shtus o hosiru shtus was a sixth higher
or a sixth... sixth lower than its actual value, מכרן בטל, mechran
batel, then the take the sale that they did to pay off
the creditors is null and void. רבן שמעון גמליאל אומר Rabban Shimon
Gamliel omer מכרן קיים. mechran kayam. Nope, the sale is still legitimate.
If a court did it, we, it has its own parameters. If
a court does it, it's binding regardless. Okay. אם כן מה כוח
בית דין יפה, im kein mah koach beis din yafeh, because if
you wouldn't say that, then what good is the power of Beis
Din? So even if they were way off in their assessment, the
sale is still valid. Okay, that's fine. But then, ואמר רב הונא
בר חיננא אמר רב נחמן, ve'amar Rav Huna bar Chinena amar Rav
Nachman, the same Rav Nachman who said מה כוח בית דין יפה
mah koach beis din yafeh by the orphans, here says הלכה כדברי
חכמים. halacha kedivrei chachamim. We rule like the Chachamim that the sale
is void. So what's your story, Rav Nachman? If a court does
something, does it can it get can it get nullified or not
nullified? By the orphans you say it's not voided, here you say
it is voided. What's the difference? So the Gemara says לא קשיא,
lo kashya, it's not difficult.
הא דטעו הא דלא טעו. ha detau ha delo tau. In one
case they made a mistake. They were off by a significant amount
of the value, and therefore it's void. So the power of the
court does not include cases where they significantly erred, where there's a
real error. Okay, but in the case by the orphans growing up,
they didn't make an error. So the Gemara says אי דלא טעו
מאי יכולים למחות? ei delo tau mai yecholim limchos? If they didn't
make an error, then what's the orphan complaining about? So no, יכלי
למחות ברווחא. yechli lemchos berevacha. He can still complain. He could say
I wanted the North field and not the East field, you know,
and I have the following reasons. There's reasons I prefer this. It's
not an objective error, it's a preference. Okay, so maybe there's three
possibilities. You don't override, the court's acts are never voided even in
the case of an error. They're voided in the case of an
error but not in the case where the person they were representing
just wasn't happy. Okay, and the third case is that even if
the person just wasn't happy, they're voided. So Rav Nachman is in
the middle position. You're not happy, you had a different preference, tough
luck, the court did it. Okay, but if it was a real
error, that's a different story. Now we continue. אמר רב נחמן, amar
Rav Nachman, so we're still going to keep in this vein for
a bit, האחים שחלקו הרי הן כלקוחות. ha'achim shechalaku harei hein kelakuchos.
Now let's say it's not a court. Let's say we have brothers
dividing an estate. Okay, it follows the same rules as normal buying
and selling. What does that mean? Purchasers. פחות משתות, pachos mishtus, if
after they'd made the division they realized that one person that they
were not exactly equal portions, you know, and that some of the
your your section of the estate was actually worth a little bit
more than mine. If the difference was less than a sixth of
the value, נקנה מקח, nikna mekach, then that doesn't affect the the
division of the estate. The same way if I sold you something
and I was off by more by less than a sixth in
either direction, it's still valid. Okay, a little overcharge, a little undercharge,
it's still valid. יתר על שתות, yeser al shtus, let's say your
portion was more than a sixth more than mine or less than
mine. Okay, so בטל
מקח. batel mekach. The same way if in a transaction I over
or undercharge you by more than a sixth, the sale is void,
here too the division is void. שתות, shtus, if I exactly one
sixth overcharge or undercharge, קנה, kana, the sale is valid, ומחזיר אונאה,
umachzir ona'ah, you have to pay back the difference. Okay, so you
would apply exactly that by a division of an estate. So if
I if your portion was less than a sixth more than mine,
it's valid. More than a sixth more than mine, it's voided, we
do the whole thing again. Exactly a sixth more or less, whatever,
it goes either direction than mine, then the division is valid, but
you have to pay me the difference of the of the two.
Let's just move a little bit. Okay, so the Gemara says
אמר רבא, amar Rava, הא דאמרן, ha de'amrinan, that which we said
פחות משתות נקנה מקח, pachos mishtus nikna mekach, that if it's less
than a sixth it's valid by an estate, okay, לא אמרן אלא
דלא שויוהו שליח. lo amran ela delo shaveihu shaliach. That's only when
the person who was dividing the estate, you know, you were dividing
you know you chose your portion and your brother chose his portion.
But if you made a agent to represent you in the negotiations
and this agent was off, you know, did not make an exact
fair division and you know you got less than a sixth, you
got yours was a little less than somebody else's, אמר לתיקוני שדרתיך
ולא לעוותי. amar letikuni shedartich velo le'avusi. Then you could say, you
know, you were my agent to represent my benefit, my interest, not
to hurt me. So as we've pointed out before, this just becomes
absurd. If I basically am going to get into a negotiation with
somebody, if you know anything you just make an agent to represent
you. And then
if after the fact you find out that he could have gotten
a better deal, then you just void the whole thing because you
could have said well the agent was there for for my benefit
and not for you know and not to hurt my interest. So
here when it says is if your agent, I don't know the
answer to that, but if you had an agent representing you in
the negotiation of dividing the estate, okay, then
then if the agent got your portion was worth a little bit
less than your brother's portion, then you can either void the sale
or maybe at least get the difference back from your brother because
you could say he wasn't my agent to to harm me, he
was only my agent for my benefit. Okay,
that's. Anyway, number one. Number two. דהא דאמרינן יתמי שתות בטל מקח,
De-ha de-amrinan yasmi shtus batel mekach, that what we say if it's
off by more than a שתות, shtus, is the whole sale is
void, לא אמרינן אלא דלא אמר נפלגין בשומא דבי דינא. lo amrin
ela de-lo amar niflagin be-shuma de-beidin. That's only now actually תוספות Tosafot's
גירסא girsa is, I'm going to read it by תוספות Tosafot's גירסא.
girsa. תוספות Tosafot's גירסא girsa is הא דאמרינן ha de-amrin if it's
שתות shtus it is, let me just double check that I got
the גירסא girsa right. Hold on.
Right, that right, תוספות Tosafot says it's the order, less than a
שתות, shtus, a שתות, shtus, more than a שתות. shtus. Okay, so
I'm going to read it תוספות Tosafot's way. תוספות Tosafot's way is
that which we said that if it's exactly a שתות, shtus, it's
valid and you give back the difference, okay, not בטל מקח, batel
mekach, it's valid and you give back the difference, לא אמרינן אלא
דלא אמר נפלגין בשומא דבי דינא. lo amrin ela de-lo amar niflagin
be-shuma de-beidin. Only if you didn't say let's divide it based on
the way the court would assess the value. אבל אמר נפלוג בשומא
דבי דינא, Aval amar niflog be-shuma de-beidin, if you said let our
division be like a division of a court, okay, what would that
mean?
Okay,
where were we?
דבי דינא de-beidin מכרן קיים. mekhran kayam. Then it would be valid
even and meaning you wouldn't have to give back the difference. Okay,
תוספות Tosafot's reading that it was exactly a שתות, shtus, that before
we taught you give back the difference, but if you said let's
treat it like a division of the court, then you don't have
to give back the difference. How do you know? דתנן, Detnan, שומא
דדיינים שפיחתו שתות או הוסיפו שתות מכרן בטל. shuma de-dayanim she-pikhsu shtus
o hosifu shtus mekhran batel. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר מכרן קיים.
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer mekhran kayam. So רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says that it's valid, okay, and we so
hold on I'm just now I'm confused again one more second.
Right, right, meaning if you said like it's a בית דין Beis
Din's division, it's a little I'm sorry if I'm just confusing things.
But anyway I'm trying to read it like תוספות, Tosafot, I'm not
sure I'm doing us any good. Okay, but anyway, okay, but by
the בית דין Beis Din like the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says that if it's a שתות shtus more
or less the sale is void, right? So let's read right okay.
You know what, let's try רש"י, Rashi, because it's the גירסא girsa
that everybody has in front of you and I'm getting confused reading
תוספות. Tosafot. Okay, let's try it again with רש"י. Rashi. Okay, because
there's problems with רש"י Rashi as well, but anyway, let's go back.
דהא דאמרינן, De-ha de-amrinan, I'll go back to the little bit in
parentheses. דהא דאמרינן יתמי שתות בטל מקח, De-ha de-amrinan yasmi shtus batel
mekach, that's what we said that if it's more than a שתות
shtus the sale is void, לא אמרינן אלא דלא אמר נפלגין בשומא
דבי דינא. lo amrin ela de-lo amar niflagin be-shuma de-beidin. That's only
if you didn't say let's treat it like a division of בית
דין. Beis Din. אבל אמר נפלוג בשומא דבי דינא, Aval amar niflog
be-shuma de-beidin, if you said let it be like a division of
בית דין, Beis Din, מכרן קיים mekhran kayam then it would be
valid. Okay, how would it be valid? דתנן, Detnan, שומא דדיינים, shuma
de-dayanim, it would not be void because we teach שומא דדיינים שפיחתו
שתות או הוסיפו שתות מכרן בטל, shuma de-dayanim she-pikhsu shtus o hosifu
shtus mekhran batel, okay well that's consistent, it is בטל. batel. אבל
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר מכרן קיים Aval Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
omer mekhran kayam and presumably רש"י Rashi says here we're following רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. So if you say, if
you say that according to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel even when בית דין Beis Din makes a mistake in the
division it's still valid, and if you said let it be like
a בית דין Beis Din division, then it would be valid even
if they were off more by more than a שתות. shtus. והא
דאמרינן שתות קנה מחזיר אונאה, Ve-ha de-amrinan shtus kana makhzir ona-ah, and
that's what we say when if it's a שתות shtus it's good
but you have to give back the difference, לא אמרינן אלא במטלטלי,
lo amrin ela be-metalteli, that's only by
chattel. אבל במקרקעי, Aval be-makharke, but if it's by land, אין אונאה
לקרקעות, ein ona-ah le-karka-os, then it,
then it wouldn't matter, even if you're way off, it would still
be valid. Okay, so now basically let's just
write this out because I'm getting a little bit confused.
Okay, we have three cases. We have if it's less than a
שתות, shtus,
it's good. If we have it more than... did I do that
right? No, other way. Less than a שתות shtus it's good, more
than a שתות shtus it's בטל, batel, and one-sixth it is good
and pay back the difference. Okay, that's the normal principle by normal
purchase and that's the principle we're saying by dividing an estate. But
now we qualify, okay, when do we say that this is good?
That's only if... but if it's a שליח, shaliach, then it's void,
because you could say I made my שליח shaliach only for my
benefit, I'm not happy with the fact that it wasn't a perfect
division. That's what we say that if it's more than a שתות
shtus it's בטל, batel, but if you said that this should be
but... okay but if you said that it's a what do you
call it, if you said let's do it like a בית דין,
Beis Din, like a בית דין, Beis Din, then we say it's
קיים, kayam, it's good. That's like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel who says מה כח בית דין יפה אם כן מה
כח בית דין יפה, ma ko-ach Beis Din yafeh in ken ma
ko-ach Beis Din yafeh, that by a בית דין Beis Din something
is always going to be good and if you said let's make
it like a בית דין, Beis Din, then it will be good.
And when we say exactly a שתות shtus you pay back the
difference, that's only if it's chattel. But if it's קרקע, karka, then
we say it's always good because there's no אונאה, ona-ah, there's no
sense of overcharging by land because maybe somewhat because it's categorically excluded
and somewhat because you know it's... It's always very hard to exactly
assess the value of land. Okay, now, by the way, that's a
huge exclusion because most of the division we normally imagine of that
would be by קרקע Karka and this makes this whole thing relevant
only by chattel, not by קרקע. Karka. So, one of the issues
that תוספות Tosafos questions is, maybe is רש"י Rashi saying the normal
sense is that קרקע Karka is always good, even if they're like
way off, even if it's like double off, it would still be
good? But since רש"י'ס Rashi's read is if it's a sixth, that's
when קרקע Karka makes a difference, maybe according to רש"י, Rashi, if
it's off by more than a sixth, maybe even by קרקע Karka
it would be no good. Okay, so how much is קרקע Karka
excluded from the laws of אונאה? Ona'ah?
It goes to a פסוק, Pasuk, he says.
Yeah, I know. Let's read a little bit more. So the גמרא
Gemara says like
this: ובמכרתיה לא אמרינן אלא דפלג בעילויה. u'bemikartei lo amrinan ela de-palag
be-iluiya. By קרקע, Karka, when we do say that even by קרקע
Karka is excluded from the laws of אונאה Ona'ah and you don't
have to pay back the difference, that's only if the error was
made in assessing the dollar value.
אבל פלג במשחתא לא, Aval palag bemishchata lo, meaning basically it was
like it's all farmland, it's all of the same value, everybody's going
to get 30 acres. Okay, and then we realize, oh, by the
way, when we drew the line we made a mistake. We drew
the line over here. You only got 28 acres and you got
32 acres. There you don't say אין אונאה בקרקע. Ein Ona'ah beKarka.
אין אונאה בקרקע Ein Ona'ah beKarka means overcharging. The dollar value assessed
was off. That was a simple question
of
measuring.
Okay, כדירבא, Kedirabba, like רבא. Rabba. דאמר רבא כל דבר שבמידה ושבמשקל
ושבמניין, De'amar Rabba kol davar she-bemiddah u'beshikkul u'beminyan, anything that's about to
be measured, right? If basically you're selling a dozen eggs for dollar
and I got 11 or I got 13, you don't say more
than a sixth, less than a sixth. That was just the number
was off, that wasn't the assessment of it was off, the price
was off. אפילו פחות מכדי אונאה נמי חוזר Afilu pachot mikedei ona'ah
nami chozer would also go back. Okay, so we will I guess
end here and then tomorrow on יום טוב Yom Tov we'll pick
up with the whole issue about שליח לדבר עבירה. shaliach lidvar aveirah.